Register of the Library of Social History Collection
Hoover Institution Archives
- General Subject File I, 1918-1994 (Box 277-293)
  - Russia and the Soviet Union
    - Russian Revolution and Civil War, 1918-1948 (Box-folder 289: 2)
      George V. Lomonossoff, Memoirs of the Russian Revolution; M. Philips Price, The Old Order in Europe and the New Order in Russia; M. Philips Price, The Soviet, the Terror and Intervention; Karl Radek and Arthur Ransome, Radek and Ransome on Russia
    - Russian Revolution and Civil War, 1918-1948 (contd.) (Box-folder 289: 3)
      Larisa Reĭsner, Sviazhsk; A. Shliapnikov, Kanun semnadtsatogo goda
    - Stalin, Joseph, 1932-1939 (Box-folder 289: 4)
      Pamphlets by Stalin: From Socialism to Communism in the Soviet Union; An Interview with the German Author Emil Ludwig; Marxism vs. Liberalism: An Interview [with H. G. Wells]; The Results of the First Five-Year Plan; Speech at the First All-Union Congress of Collective Farm Shock Brigade Workers; Work in the Rural Districts
    - Women, 1921-1984 (Box-folder 289: 5)
      Aleksandra Kollontaĭ, The Peasant and Working Woman in Soviet Russia; Alexandra Kollontai, Women Workers Struggle for their Rights
    - Women, 1921-1984 (contd.) (Box-folder 289: 6)
      The Marriage Laws of Soviet Russia; The Soviet Law on Marriage
  - Science. J. D. Bernal, Engels and Science, undated (Box-folder 290: 1)
  - Spain. Georgi Dimitrov, Spain and the People's Front, 1937 (Box-folder 292: 1)
  - United States, 1935-1972 (Box-folder 292: 2)
    Anne Braden, House Un-American Activities Committee: Bulwark of Segregation; Gus Hall, A Lame Duck in Turbulent Waters: The Next 4 Years of Nixon; A. B. Magil, The Truth about Father Coughlin; Draft for a Program for the Socialist Party of the United States; We Accuse McCarthyism; Who Are the 18 Prisoners in the Minneapolis Labor Case?
  - Vietnam, 1947-1980 (Box-folder 292: 3)
    Anh-Van and Jacqueline Roussel, Mouvements nationaux et lutte de classes au Viet-nam; Inprecor/Intercontinental Press special issue on Indochina
  - Women. Hildegart, La revolución sexual, bound with David Riazanov, Socialismo y matrimonio, undated (Box-folder 292: 4)
  - Yugoslavia, 1948-1952 (Box-folder 292: 5)
    Edvard Kardelj, Socialist Democracy; C. P. D. Kurup, Yugoslavia at Crossroads; Mosha Piyade, About the Legend that the Yugoslav Uprising Owed Its Existence to Soviet Assistance; Aleksandar Rankovic, Report on the Organizational Work of the CPY
  - Yugoslavia, 1948-1952 (contd.) (Box-folder 292: 6)
    Josip Broz Tito, Political Report [1948 and 1949]; Josip Broz Tito, Real Reasons behind the Slanders against Yugoslavia; Josip Broz Tito, Workers Manage Factories in Yugoslavia
  - Yugoslavia, 1948-1952 (contd.) (Box-folder 292: 7)
    The Correspondence between the Central Committee of the Communist Party of Yugoslavia and the Central Committee of the All-Union Communist Party (Bolsheviks); Letters of the CC CPY and the CC CPSU(b); Program of the Communist Party of Yugoslavia; Statement of the Central Committee of the Communist Party of Yugoslavia; Statute of the Communist Party of Yugoslavia; Unprincipled and Unjust Accusations of the CPY
  - Zinoviev Letter. W. P. Coates, The "Zinoviev Letter": The Case for a Full Investigation, 1928 (Box-folder 292: 8)
- Monographs I, 1902-1996 (Box 293-306)
  - Algeria. Mohammed Harbi, Aux origines du Front de Libération Nationale, 1975 (Box-folder 293: 1)
  - Argentina, 1956-1996 (Box 293)
    - Osvaldo Coggiola, Historia del trotskismo argentino, 1929-1965 (Box-folder 293: 2)
    - Félix Luna, Argentina de Peron a Lanusse, 1943-1973 (Box-folder 293: 3)
    - Nahuel Moreno, El golpe gorila de 1955 (Box-folder 293: 4)
    - Rodolfo Puiggros, Historia critica de los partidos politicos argentinos (Box-folder 293: 5)
    - Jorge Abelardo Ramos, Revolució n y contrarrevolució n en la Argentina (Box-folder 293: 6)
    - Ernesto Gonzalez, El trotskismo obrero e internacionalista en la Argentina, 1960-1985, 2 volumes (Box-folder 293: 7-8)
  - Australia, 1977-1984 (Box 293: 9-10)
  - Bolivia, 1963-1978 (Box 294)
    - Guillermo Lora, Contribución a la historia politica de Bolivia (Box-folder 294: 1)
    - Guillermo Lora, Miguel Alandia (Box-folder 294: 2)
    - Guillermo Lora, La revolución boliviana (Box-folder 294: 3)
  - Brazil. Na contracorrente da história: Documentos da Liga Comunista Internacionalista, 1930-1933, 1986 (Box-folder 294: 4)
  - Bukharin, Nikolai, 1920-1982 (Box 294: 5-11)
    - The Communist Programme of World Revolution (Box-folder 294: 5)
    - Historical Materialism (Box-folder 294: 6)
    - Imperializm i nakoplenie kapitala (Box-folder 294: 7)
    - Lenin as a Marxist (Box-folder 294: 8)
    - Lenin marxista (Box-folder 294: 9)
    - Marxism and Modern Thought (with others) (Box-folder 294: 10)
    - Selected Writings on the State and the Transition to Socialism (Box-folder 294: 11)
  - Chile, 1962-1980 (Box 295)
    - Lisandro Otero, Razón y fuerza de Chile (Box-folder 295: 1)
    - Luis Vitale, Esencia y apariencia de la democracia cristiana (Box-folder 295: 2)
    - Luis Vitale, Historia del movimiento obrero (Box-folder 295: 3)
    - Luis Vitale, Interpretación marxista de la historia de Chile (Box-folder 295: 4)
    - La tragedia chilena (Box-folder 295: 5)
  - China, 1976-1983 (Box 295)
    - Peng Shuzhi, L'envol du communisme en Chine (Box-folder 295: 6)
    - La Question chinoise dans l'Internationale communiste, 1926-1927 (Box-folder 295: 7)
  - Communist International, 1920-1934 (Box 295)
    - R. Palme Dutt, The Two Internationals (Box-folder 295: 8)
    - Clara Zetkin, The Toilers against War (Box-folder 295: 9)
    - Theses, Reports, Speeches of the Thirteenth Plenum of the Executive Committee of the Communist International (Box-folder 295: 10)
  - Cuba, 1959-1996 (Box 296)
    - Diana Abad, De la guerra grande al partido revolucionario cubano (Box-folder 296: 1)
    - José Cantón Navarro, Historia de Cuba (Box-folder 296: 2)
    - Domingo García Cárdenas, State Organization in Cuba (Box-folder 296: 3)
    - José Martí, La edad de oro (Box-folder 296: 4)
    - José Martí, El indio de nuestra América (Box-folder 296: 5)
    - Victor Pérez-Galdós, Un hombre que actua como piensa (Box-folder 296: 6)
    - J. Posadas, Sobre la revolución socialista en Cuba (Box-folder 296: 7)
    - Pedro Vuskovic and Belarmino Elgueta, Che Guevara en el presente de la América Latina (Box-folder 296: 8)
    - Biobibliografia de Carlos Rafael Rodriguez (Box-folder 296: 9)
    - Cuba: La revolución de 1895 y el fin del imperio colonial español (Box-folder 296: 10)
    - The Cuban Revolution and Its Extension (Box-folder 296: 11)
    - XV Congreso de la CTC (Box-folder 296: 12)
    - Encuentra latinoaméricano y del Caribe (Box-folder 296: 13)
    - The Five Summit Conferences of the Non-Aligned Countries (Box-folder 297: 1)
    - Maceo: Dos conferencias histó ricas (Box-folder 297: 2)
    - Marxistas de América (Box-folder 297: 3)
    - La Participación en Cuba y los retos del futuro (Box-folder 297: 4)
    - El Presidio político en Cuba (Box-folder 297: 5)
    - Primer congreso del Partido Comunista de Cuba, 2 volumes (Box-folder 297: 6)
    - Turcios lima (Box-folder 297: 7)
  - El Salvador. Rafael Menjívar, Formació n y lucha del proletariado industrial salvadoreño, 1982 (Box-folder 298: 1)
  - France, 1921-1975 (Box 298)
    - Daniel Bensaïd and Henri Weber, Mai 1968 (Box-folder 298: 2)
    - Yvan Craipeau, Le mouvement trotskyste en France (Box-folder 298: 3)
    - Pierre Naville, L'entre-deux guerres (Box-folder 298: 4)
    - Jacqueline Pluet-Despatin, La presse trotskiste en France de 1926 à 1968 (Box-folder 298: 5)
    - C. Talès, La commune de 1871 (with preface by Leon Trotsky) (Box-folder 298: 6)
    - Edith Thomas, Pauline Roland (Box-folder 298: 7)
  - Germany, 1921-1975. (Box 298)
    - Robert Black, Fascism in Germany, 2 volumes (Box-folder 298: 8)
    - Grigorii Zinoviev, Zwölf Tage in Deutschland (Box-folder 298: 9)
  - Great Britain, 1916-1990. (Box 298)
    - Tariq Ali, Street Fighting Years (Box-folder 298: 10)
    - Sam Bornstein and Al Richardson, The War and the International: A History of the Trotskyist Movement in Britain, 1937-1949 (Box-folder 298: 11)
    - Reg Groves, Sharpen the Sickle! The History of the Farm Workers' Union (Box-folder 298: 12)
  - Great Britain, 1916-1990 (contd.). (Box 299)
    - Mark Jenkins, Bevanism: Labour's High Tide (Box-folder 299: 1)
    - John Pepper, The General Strike and the General Betrayal (Box-folder 299: 2)
    - R. W. Postgate et al., A Workers' History of the Great Strike (Box-folder 299: 3)
    - Th. Rothstein, From Chartism to Labourism (Box-folder 299: 4)
    - Hermann Schlüter, Die Chartisten-Bewegung (Box-folder 299: 5)
    - About Turn: The British Communist Party and the Second World War (Box-folder 299: 6)
  - Guatemala. Intervention of International Communism in Guatemala (U.S. Department of State publication), 1954 (Box-folder 299: 7)
  - Guyana. Cheddi Jagan, The West on Trial: The Fight for Guyana's Freedom, 1972 (Box-folder 299: 8)
  - Honduras. Victor Meza, Historia del movimiento obrero hondureño, 1980 (Box-folder 299: 9)
  - Hungary, 1956-1957. (Box 299)
    - Herbert Aptheker, The Truth about Hungary (Box-folder 299: 10)
    - Peter Fryer, Hungarian Tragedy (Box-folder 299: 11)
  - India. A. G. Noorani, The Kashmir Question, 1964 (Box-folder 299: 12)
  - Japan. Sen Katayama, The Labor Movement in Japan, 1918 (Box-folder 299: 13)
  - Marxism, 1902-1978 (Box 300)
    - Edward Aveling, The Student's Marx (Box-folder 300: 1)
    - Karl Kautsky, The Social Revolution (Box-folder 300: 2)
    - Guillermo Lora, Revolución y foquismo (Box-folder 300: 3)
    - A. Lozovskii, Marx and the Trade Unions (Box-folder 300: 4)
    - Karl Marx et al., Communist Morality (Box-folder 300: 5)
    - World Communist Movement, Volumes I, III-IV (U.S. Congress House Committee on Un-American Activities publication) (Box-folder 300: 6)
  - Mexico, 1970-1986 (Box 300)
    - Valentín Campa S., Mi testimonio (Box-folder 300: 7)
    - Juan Gómez-Quiñones, Sembradores: Ricardo Flores Magón y el Partido Liberal Mexicano (Box-folder 300: 8)
    - Elena Poniatowska, La noche de Tlatelolco (Box-folder 300: 9)
    - Paco Ignacio Taibo II, Los bolshevikis: Historia narrativa de los orígenes del comunismo en México (Box-folder 300: 10)
    - Los Procesos de México 68 (Box-folder 300: 11)
  - Moscow Trials, 1936-1972 (Box 301)
    - Victor Serge, 16 fusillés à Moscou (Box-folder 301: 1)
    - Report of Court Proceedings (3 volumes): The Case of the Trotskyite-Zinovievite Terrorist Centre (Box-folder 301: 2)
    - The Case of the Anti-Soviet Trotskyite Centre (Box-folder 301: 3)
    - The Case of the Anti-Soviet "Bloc of Rights and Trotskyites" (Box-folder 301: 4)
  - Palestine, 1967-1979 (Box 301)
    - Musa Budeiri, The Palestine Communist Party (Box-folder 301: 5)
    - Sami Hadawi, Bitter Harvest (Box-folder 301: 6)
  - Peru, 1955-1970 (Box 301)
    - Héctor Béjar, Les guérillas péruviennes de 1965 (Box-folder 301: 7)
    - Héctor Béjar, Peru 1965 (Box-folder 301: 8)
    - José Carlos Mariátegui, El proletariado y su organización (Box-folder 301: 9)
    - José Carlos Mariátegui, Siete ensayos de interpretación de la realidad peruana (Box-folder 301: 10)
  - Red International of Labor Unions, 1928-1931 (Box 302)
    - A. Lozovskii, La grève est un combat! (Box-folder 302: 1)
    - Report of the Fourth Congress of the R.I.L.U. (Box-folder 302: 2)
  - Russia and the Soviet Union, 1925-1971 (Box 302-303)
    - Tsesiliia Bobrovskaia, Twenty Years in Underground Russia (Box-folder 302: 3)
    - James Bunyan, Intervention, Civil War, and Communism in Russia (Box-folder 302: 4)
    - Isaac Deutscher, Lenin's Childhood (Box-folder 302: 5)
    - Isaac Deutscher, Soviet Trade Unions (Box-folder 302: 6)
    - Alice Withrow Field, Protection of Women and Children in Soviet Russia (Box-folder 302: 7)
    - B. Jarotsky, The Russian Trade Unions and the Struggle for Unity (Box-folder 302: 8)
    - Nikita Khrushchev, An Account to the Party and the People (Box-folder 302: 9)
    - Nadezhda Krupskaia, Soviet Woman (Box-folder 302: 10)
    - Maksim Litvinov, The Bolshevik Revolution (Box-folder 302: 11)
    - George M. Price, Labor Protection in Soviet Russia (Box-folder 302: 12)
    - Karl Radek, Les voies de la révolution russe (Box-folder 302: 13)
    - Gérard Rosenthal, Mémoire pour la réhabilitation de Zinoviev (Box-folder 302: 14)
    - Jessica Smith, Woman in Soviet Russia (Box-folder 302: 15)
    - Grigory Zinovyev, Russia's Path to Communism (Box-folder 302: 16)
    - Les Bolcheviks contre Staline, 1923-1928 (Box-folder 303: 1)
    - Foreign Relations of the United States: 1919, Russia (U.S. Department of State publication) (Box-folder 303: 2)
    - Otchet Tsentral'noi Kontrol'noi Komissii RKP(b), XIV s'ezdu partii (Box-folder 303: 3)
  - Science, 1948-1954 (Box 303)
    - J. D. Bernal and Maurice Cornforth, Science for Peace and Socialism (Box-folder 303: 4)
    - O. B. Lepeshinskaya, The Origin of Cells from Living Substance (Box-folder 303: 5)
    - Trofim Lysenko, Agrobiology (Box-folder 303: 6)
    - Trofim Lysenko, Heredity and Its Variability (Box-folder 303: 7)
    - Trofim Lysenko, The Science of Biology Today (Box-folder 303: 8)
    - Scientific Session on the Physiological Teachings of Academician I. P. Pavlov (Box-folder 303: 9)
  - South Africa, 1960-1988 (Box 303-304)
    - Ken Luckhardt and Brenda Wall, Organize or Starve! The History of the South African Congress of Trade Unions (Box-folder 303: 10)
    - Francis Meli, South Africa Belongs to Us: A History of the ANC (Box-folder 303: 11)
    - Bernard Sachs, The Road from Sharpeville (Box-folder 304: 1)
    - I. B. Tabata, The Awakening of a People (Box-folder 304: 2)
    - I. B. Tabata, Education for Barbarism in South Africa (Box-folder 304: 3)
    - South African Communists Speak (Box-folder 304: 4)
  - Spain, 1966-1978 (Box 304)
    - Joaquín Maurín, Revolució n y contrarrevolución en España (Box-folder 304: 5)
    - Revista comunismo, 1931-1934 (Box-folder 304: 6)
  - Trotsky, Leon, 1923-1990 (Box 304-305)
    - Max Eastman, Leon Trotsky: The Portrait of a Youth (Box-folder 304: 7)
    - Julian Gorkin, L'assassinat de Trotsky (Box-folder 304: 8)
    - Isaac Don Levine, The Mind of an Assassin (Box-folder 304: 9)
    - Nicholas Mosley, The Assassination of Trotsky (Box-folder 304: 10)
    - Leandro A. Sanchez Salazar, Murder in Mexico (Box-folder 304: 11)
    - Leon Trotsky, [ Diary in Exile, 1935. Chinese translation] (Box-folder 305: 1)
    - Leon Trotsky, Geschichte der russischen Revolution (Box-folder 305: 2)
    - Leon Trotsky, Die russische Revolution 1905 (Box-folder 305: 3)
    - Leon Trotsky, Schriften, Volumes I.1 and I.2 (Box-folder 305: 4)
    - Leon Trotsky, Schriften, Volumes II.1 and II.2 (Box-folder 306: 1)
    - Leon Trotsky, Stalins Verbrechen (Box-folder 306: 2)
    - Leon Trotsky, 1917: Uroki oktiabria (bound with Lev Kamenev and Joseph Stalin, Leninizm ili Trotskizm?) (Box-folder 306: 3)
  - Uruguay. Carlos Wilson, The Tupamaros, 1974 (Box-folder 306: 4)
- Audiovisual File, 1920-1937 (Box 307)
  Photographs, postcards and printed reproduction of a drawing.
  - Snapshots of unidentified indviduals at the Leon Trotsky compound, Coyoacán, Mexico, circa 1937-1940 (Box-folder 307: 1)
  - Printed reproduction of drawing of John Reed, 1920 (Box-folder 307: 2)
  - Partido Obrero de Unificación Marxista postcards, Spain, circa 1936-1937 (Box-folder 307: 3)
  - Mounted photographs of revolutionary activities, signs and posters in Barcelona, Spain, mainly involving the Partido Obrero de Unificación Marxista, 1937 (Box-folder 307: 4)
- Oversize File, 1917-2000 (Box 307)
  Oversize printed portfolio and armband.
  - Krasnaia Gvardiia armband, Russia, 1917 (Box-folder 307: 5)
  - Portfolio of special Cuban newspaper issues relating to the question of return of the Cuban child Elián González to Cuba from the United States, 1999-2000 (Box-folder 307: 6)
- Incremental Materials, Part II, 1960-2010 (Box 308-310)
- General Subject File II, 1960-1968. (Box 308-310)
  Pamphlet, serial issue and photocopies of printed matter
  - Bolivia. Tricontinental special supplement on guerrilla war in Bolivia, 1968 (Box-folder 308: 1)
  - Cuba, 1960-1965 (Box 308-310)
  - Dorticós, Osvaldo, Committed to Our Own Principles (pamphlet), 1962 (Box-folder 308: 2)
  - Guevara, Ché (Box 308-310)
    - Articles in Verde Olivo, 1960. Printed copies (Box-folder 308: 3)
    - El Ché en la revolución cubana (documentary publication), 1966. Substantially complete photocopies of printed volumes (Box 308-310)
      - Contents of Volumes 1-6 (Box-folder 308: 4)
      - Volume 1 [articles and letters] (Box-folder 308: 5)
      - Volume 2 [speeches, 1958-1960] (Box-folder 308: 6)
      - Volume 3 [speeches, 1961] (Box-folder 308: 7)
      - Volume 4 [speeches, 1962-1963] (Box-folder 309: 1)
      - Volume 5 [speeches, 1964-1965] (Box-folder 309: 2)
      - Volume 6 [Ministry of Industry meetings] (Box-folder 309: 3)
      - Volume 7 [guerrilla warfare episodes] (Box-folder 310: 1)
- Monographs II, 1964-2010 (Box 310)
  - Cuba, 1989-2010. Jesús Arboleya Cervera, La contrarrevolución cubana; Fidel Castro, La contraofensiva estratégica; Fidel Castro, La victoria estratégica; Fernando Martínez Heredia, Ché, el socialism y el comunismo (Box 310)
  - Marxism, 1964. Karl Marx, Economic and Philosphic Manuscripts of 1844 (Box 310)
  - Military theory, 1972. Marxism-Leninism on War and Army (Soviet publication reissued by the U.S. Air Force) (Box 310)
  - Nicaragua, 1985. Emilio Quintana, Bananos (Box 310)